Ely Samuel Parker Papers 1794-1946 Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1794-1946; 1.5 linear feet
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 June 23; Moore, F. H. (Box 3)
    A reply to Ely's letter of June 21, acknowledging receipt of the books, and concluding with a discussion of national politics.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1852 June 26; Wilson, Peter (Box 3)
    A request that Nic call on Mr. Scoville of W.C. Little and Co.'s book store to make certain adjustments on a subscription to Merry's Museum and Parley Magazine ordered sent to his son, Rush Spencer Wilson.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1852 June 30; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Ely will try to be at Batavia to enter protest at land sale and does not believe that the sale should cause worry on his father's part.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1852 July 7; Pierce, Daniel W. (Box 3)
    A school friend reports from South Valley that he called on Robert [?] Watt as requested and was told that an annuity payment of $4.75 has been "left in the care of Peter Crouse, who lives in Coldspring," but that the payment six years in arrears is not ready.
  - ALS to William Linn Brown, 1852 July 16; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Ely writes at the request of the widow Blacksmith to explain and apologize for being dilatory in acknowledging a letter of condolence written by Brown sometime last summer. Brown's letter was taken from the Post Office by J.A. Sanford and not delivered because of Sanford's death. Ely's letter is signed as "Chief and Successor to Blacksmith."
  - ALS to J. D. Fay, 1852 Aug. 7; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter enclosing estimates of engineering expenses and reporting that cholera deaths are declining in Rochester.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Aug. 12; Hall, B. F. (Box 3)
    A superintendent of the Thomas Indian School writes at the suggestion of a Mr. Thompson for confirmation of an Iroquois tradition concerning Logan, a Cayuga chief, to whose memory it is proposed to erect a monument near his birthplace. Brantz Mayer, President of the Maryland Historical Society, `in an effort to redeem the character of the Cresap family with which he has connections, has contradicted facts of Logan's life long held by early settlers.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Aug. 21; Parker, Caroline (Box 3)
    A newsy letter from home reporting that Caroline has postponed until Spring her plan to earn needed money teaching, because she has not been well and is kept very busy with household chores. Mary Jemison died July 18. Nic and Dr. Wilson have been home on a visit. She discusses the tenants' farm crops and Levi Parker's drinking and love affairs.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Sept. 9; Parker, William H. (Box 3)
    Letter giving measurements and diagrams of farm land leased to White and Burns. Mutilated - part of second page missing.
  - AMs, 1852 Sept. 22; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Comment on an attached newspaper clipping from the Rochester Advertiser, in which Ely claims his statement as to how he would vote, if he possessed the franchise, has been misrepresented. The clipping refers to his speech at a rally for the democratic nominees in the national elections.
  - ALS to B. F. Hall, 1852 Oct. 14; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Typewritten copy of a published reply to Hall's inquiry of Aug. 12, in which Ely outlines the Iroquois `traditional history' concerning Chief Logan.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1852 Oct. 15; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter of brotherly advice concerning Newton's health, school work and clothing. Ely expects to be at Cattaraugus when the annuities are paid and "to make some fuss among the Indians" in connection with the Stryker money.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Oct. 30; Parker, Newton I. (Box 3)
    A letter of thanks for some clothes which `suit well all over and all around.' Nic and Lucia Green are back at school and there are 12 Iroquois students, two more than the number limited by law. Newton's neck is getting better.
  - ALS to J. H. Martindale, 1852 Nov. 9; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 3)
    A letter of appreciation prompted by the favorable results of suits in the Court of Appeals. Timber is being taken by settlers and they would like Martindale to devise a means by which the Indians may receive compensation.
  - ALS to [Nicholson H. Parker?], 1852 Nov. 25; Tyrell, Amos (Box 3)
    Fragment of mutilated letter, commenting on social and educational opportunities available in Albany, the successful outcome of the Tonawanda suits in the Court of Appeals, etc.
  - ALS to L. Lea, 1852 Nov. 27; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs about the non-payment by the Indian Agent of the "Stryker defalcation" and other annuities, stressing the Tonawandas' need of the money and their autonomy within the Seneca tribe.
  - "The Canal and its Revenues", 1852 Nov. 29; Albany Evening Journal (Box 3)
    An editorial discussing an accompanying financial report of Nov. 11 by the Auditor of the Canal Fund to the Commissioners.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Dec. 13; Lapham, E. G. (Box 3)
    A letter stating that according to inquiries Dr. Fleming is "a gentleman of integrity and pecuniary responsibility."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Feb. 16; Wheat, John D. (Box 4)
    A letter from an applicant for the office of Indian Agent for New York State, soliciting Ely's influence on his behalf and mentioning as references Hon. R.C. Fenton and former Indian agents Washburn and Angel.
  - ADfS, 1853 [Feb. 18?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A recommendation of J. D. Wheat for the New York Indian sub-agency. A rough draft, signed as Grand Sachem of the Six Nations of Indians in New York and Canada.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Feb. 20; Warren, R. B. (Box 4)
    A letter from an old friend, discussing current national politics, which may result in Warren, a Whig, losing his office as postmaster at Alabama, in favor of Mr. Johnson, a Democrat.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Feb. 21; Howe, Chester (Box 4)
    A letter giving information concerning title to land on the Oil Spring Reservation, purchased by the Holland Land Co. and currently claimed by Governor Seymour and others.
  - DS Cy, 1853 Feb. 22; Conrad, C. M. (Box 4)
    Copy of a statement by the Secretary of War that the filing of the "document purporting to be the Award or Report of Horace Gay and Ira Cook" is a formality that does not determine the legality or validity of the document.
  - ALS to Tonawanda Chiefs, 1853 Feb. 23; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Letter of instructions concerning the methods the Indians should pursue, should the Sheriff receive warrants to eject White settlers, and advising that the improvement money in Pringle's hands need cause no fear, because according to the decision of the Court of Appeals, no appraisal of improvements has yet been made and without it the Ogden Co. cannot claim title to the land.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Mar. 4; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Letter advising that Asa Cutler and two others have been notified by the Sheriff to remove from their residences and stating that William Parker would like the Sachem's advice with regard to calling on the Cattaraugus Indians as witnesses, should the evicted settlers contest their rights.
  - Broadside, 1853 Mar. 8; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Printed announcement of "Indian Historical Lectures, by Ga-i-wah-go-wa" [N. H. Parker] in full Indian costume in Seminary Hall, Canandaigua.
  - ALS to the President of the U.S., 1853 Mar. 21; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A request, signed as Grand Sachem of the Six Nations of Indians in New York and Canada, that Peter Wilson be continued as interpreter for the New York Indian agency.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Mar. 21; Wilson, Peter (Box 4)
    Letter advising that J.D. Wheat has arrived in Albany, thereby missing Ely's letter of recommendation and requesting that another be sent to Wilson by return mail to enable Wilson "to proceed immediately to the South."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Mar. 22; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864 (Box 4)
    Letter calling Osburn's unfavorable report of the Tonawandas to Ely's notice. Schoolcraft presumes the new agent will be a "compromise Democrat."
  - ALS to Henry R. Schoolcraft, 1853 Mar. 25; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    An acknowledgment of Schoolcraft's letter, in which Ely refutes Osborn's assertion the Tonawandas are "surely but slowly retrograding," but agreeing with him that the old form of government should be restored at Cattaraugus and Allegany.
  - ALS to Nathan Bristol, 1853 Apr. 3; Onondaga Chiefs (Box 4)
    Draft of a letter of thanks to a New York senator "for the promptness with which the Assembly Bill for the survey of the Onondagas' Indian lands was repudiated." The survey was to be made for the purpose of apportioning the land to individual Indians, "thereby destroying that bond of common interest which unites and holds Indian communities together."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Apr. 15; Parker, Newton I. (Box 4)
    A request for advice in settling a dispute about the proportionate division of farm land at Tonawanda between the lessees, Burns and White.
  - ALS to [Ely S.?] Parker, 1853 [July?] 4; LaGrange, I. (Box 4)
    Social note apologizing for not bidding him and Sophy goodbye before they left Binghamton.
  - ALS to Caroline Parker, 1853 Apr. 23; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A brief acknowledgment of a gift sent by Newton.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 May 10; Manypenny, George W. (Box 4)
    A letter from the Commissioner of Indian Affairs advising that Marcus H. Johnson will succeed S. Osborne as sub-agent for the New York Indians, and that settlement of the Stryker defalcation fund has been delayed because of a claim set up by the Buffalo band of Senecas, the validity of which will be decided upon shortly.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 June 10; Parker, William H. (Box 4)
    A letter advising that $400 has been collected for Ely's trip to Washington and that the new agent, Marcus Johnson, has written a letter stating the Stryker money will be paid as soon as he has been informed by the Indians of the results of their census.
  - ADfS to [George W. Manypenny], 1853 [June 15?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Draft of a letter dealing with the following matters: 1) Recall of Benjamin Pringle; 2) Payment of annuities directly to the Tonawandas and their recognition as a separate band; 3) Cognizance of the fact that Phillip E. Thomas was appointed representative in Washington of the Cattaraugus and Allegheny Senecas only - that he does not represent the views or sentiments of the Tonawandas who were not included in the Act of incorporation; 4) Protest against the unfavorable report of Agent Osborn dated Sept. 30, 1852.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 July 5; Parker, Caroline (Box 4)
    Letter telling of disputes with the Cattaraugus band over the Tonawandas' share of the Stryker fund and other monies. The Tonawandas are opposed to the Cattaraugus plan to appropriate the money for the erection and maintenance of an Indian school. Newton has written that he likes Indiana.
  - ALS to Caroline Parker, 1853 Aug. 7; Parker, Newton I. (Box 4)
    A letter from Girard, Pa. stating he is happy and "getting better all the while since I began to have a little exercise." Newton and Henry hope to be able to send money home in about two weeks. Asks that mail be sent to Pittsburgh, Pa., addressed to him as "Okatawaule (Indian Chief)" a name bestowed on him by Washburn whom he has met in his travels.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Sept. 6; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Ely has received a complaint through William Jimeson that Nic has withheld money due to Harriette. Nic writes his brother to explain that he withheld the money temporarily until Harriette would consent to deducting money she owes William Parker from the amount given to Nic for her.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1853 Sept. 23; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 4)
    A request that Ely find time to see Mr. Henry Ely of Rochester who wants to talk to him about a building to be erected by Star and Childs.
  - ALS to H. S. Randall, 1853 Oct. 15; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Handwritten copy of a letter to the Secretary of State [!], the original of which is in the New York Public Library, concerning Ely's misinterpretation of the provisions of an Act limiting the number of Indian pupils, which had led to their selection on the basis of reservations instead of on population.
  - ALS to Henry S. Randall, 1853 Oct. 27; Parker, William H. (Box 4)
    An account of expenditures for "the education of Indian youths at Tonawanda," from the Trustee to the Superintendent of Common Schools, covering the period June 22 to Aug. 29.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1853 Oct. 28; Johnson, Henry W. (Box 4)
    A letter from the Deputy Superintendent of Common Schools, returning Parker's statement and pointing out that receipts as well as expenditures are required by Chapter 351 of the Law of 1851.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Jan. 2; Stockton, S. R. P. (Box 4)
    A letter from a friend now working as Foreign Money Teller for the American Express Bank, inquiring about former canal associates.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Jan. 3; Edwards, Howard (Box 4)
    The writer suggests an exchange of letters `for our own amusement and instruction' dealing with Indian history and ethnology.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Jan. 5; McClure, William (Box 4)
    A letter from a friend spending the winter in Iowa City "in the honorable employment of lobbying," containing comments on politics and social life in Iowa and references to mutual friends.
  - ALS to [Ely S.?] Parker, 1854 May 18; Drew, W. H. (Box 4)
    Note addressed to "Sir Knight Parker" requesting remittance in the amount of $8.00 for embroidered gauntlets.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 June 5; Parker, William H. (Box 4)
    Ely's advice is needed about renting a house which some prospective tenants wish to convert into a grist mill at a cost of about $20,000.
  - N.E. [?] Strong to Caroline Parker, 1854 June 5; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Note advising that someone should pick up tickets for return fares from Buffalo to Syracuse, which have been secured at half price through Mr. Stockton.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 June 22; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    A request for information concerning ownership of the Oil Spring Reservation, title to which is claimed by Jake Shongo, Ben Chamberlain and lawyer Hammon.
  - ALS to [Ely S.?] Parker, 1854 Aug. 17; Cornwal, William (Box 4)
    A suggestion that the Iroquois Indians still own the Thousand Islands on the Canadian side of the border, which according to rumor are not claimed by the government.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Aug. 19; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    The State has appropriated $40,000 to the Oneidas for land sold by them or their forefathers. Descendants of this tribe, settled at Onondaga and Allegany, wish to employ Ely and Nic to claim their share of the money.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Aug. 29; Fairchild, H. S. (Box 4)
    The Colonel acknowledges Ely's apology, refuses his resignation from the regiment, and promises that when he retires "no one will do more to have you promoted than I."
  - Announcement of Council Meeting, 1854 Oct. 24; Two Guns, Henry (Box 4)
    An announcement, printed in Seneca and English, of a Council to be held at Cattaraugus Reservation to decide upon an amendment to the Constitution of the Seneca Nation.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Oct. 27; McClure, William H. (Box 4)
    Describes his trip from Rochester to Cedar Falls, Iowa, in the company of Hank Packard and his family, with references to mutual friends encountered en route.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Nov. 22; Johnson, Anna C. (Box 4)
    A letter requesting "a little counsel and assistance" for her forthcoming book which will "tell the bright side of the story concerning Indian life and character." Her book on "The Iroquois..." was published 1855 under the pseudonym Minnie Myrtle.
  - ALS to Caroline Parker, 1854 Nov. 30; Jemison, C. C. (Box 4)
    Letter from a correspondent attending school in Albany, inquiring about Newton's whereabouts and wishing him success with his `managery.' Suggests she write to P.H. Jimerson, `a nice young man' at Jonesville.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1854 Dec. 3; Avery, Charles P. (Box 4)
    Letter of introduction for Theron Seymour of Oswego.
  - ALS to Ontario Bank, Canandaigua, 1854 Dec. 4; Manypenny, George W. (Box 4)
    The Commissioner calls attention to the Act of June 27, 1846 whereby the funds held in trust for the Senecas by the Bank cannot be transferred to the custody of the U.S. without the consent of the Indians.
  - ALS to [Ely S.] Parker, 1854 Dec. 11; Seymour, Theron (Box 4)
    Advises the deep snow prevented his reaching Tonawanda. Would appreciate Ely's securing for him the services of some of Washburn's men `when they come home' and of his brother [Newton] who is in the South.
  - Military Association of the State of New York, 1855 Jan. 9 (Box 4)
    Circular, addressed to Ely S. Parker, announcing the third annual convention of the Association in New York City.
  - Council of the Seneca Nation, 1855 Jan. 26 (Box 4)
    A resolution, signed by Henry Two Guns, as President, and Maris B. Pierce, as Clerk, that the Tonawanda Band receive their per capita share of the Greig and Gibson fund.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1855 Feb. 7; Wright, Asher (Box 4)
    A chatty letter describing Albany's celebration of the Whig victory. Wright advises confidentially that if and when Peter Wilson is displaced as interpreter, Nic should "take steps to fill the vacancy." The American Bible Society has promised aid and Wright hopes Nick will soon finish translating John. There are brief references to Minnie [Myrtle], Newton, John Hudson and others.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1855 Feb. 12; Howe, Chester (Box 4)
    A discussion of the transfer of the Greig and Gibson fund.
  - ALS to J. [?] Manypenny, 1855 Feb. 12; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A request for information concerning the measures decided upon by the Department of Indian Affairs "respecting the anticipated payment...of the Greig and Gibson annuity."
  - ALS to E.S. Parker, 1855 Feb. 13; Ontario Bank, Canandaigua (Box 4)
    The Bank will transfer the trust fund to the President of the United States on June 1.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1855 Feb. 15; Parker, Caroline (Box 4)
    Cousin William Moses would like Ely to secure a job on a farm for his 14 year old son. Newton is in Hartford, Conn. The family want Ely to use his influence in persuading Newton to return home, away from the influence of Jesse Jemison, a married woman.
  - ALS to John Lathrop, 1855 June 6; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A request for the Division Engineer's advice on how to handle a difficult situation. Mr. Britton refuses to "quit work" unless served with a written notice.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1855 June 11; White, G. W. (Box 4)
    A recommendation of a man named Hine for a position as rodman or leveler.
  - Cost estimates, 1855 [June? 1855?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Cost data on locks nos. 65 and 66, assigned to Jesse Peterson and Charles H. Britton.
  - ALS to [Newton?] Parker, 1855 Oct. 17; Jemison, C. C. (Box 4)
    A letter stating the writer is glad to be away from Cattaraugus, "a miserable place," and advising of a change of address to 184 Lancaster Street, Albany.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1855 Nov. 3; Martindale, J. H. (Box 4)
    Note advising that a communication from the chiefs should be published "as is" without revision.
  - ALS to [Nicholson?] Parker, 1855 Nov. 4; Parker, Caroline (Box 4)
    A brief letter addressed to Dr. Parker, stating she is glad he is studying medicine, and advising she is thinking of going to school this winter, requesting that he make an application to the Superintendent at Albany for her.
  - ALS to [Nicholson?] Parker, 1856 Mar. 6; Parker, Caroline (Box 4)
    Caroline writes that she is "teaching now and board myself." Father won't know until April when the trial comes up whether Nic will be needed in Albany. There are "all sorts of flying stories" in Tonawanda because C[hauncy] C. Jemison has called on Caroline.
  - Cattaraugus Reservation, 1856 Apr. 29 (Box 4)
    Minutes of "Old Party Caucus" with names of officers nominated.
  - Commercial Bank of N.J., Perth Amboy, 1856 July 10 (Box 4)
    A one dollar bill.
  - ALS to [Ely S.?] Parker, 1856 July 28; Denton, D. H. (Box 4)
    An invitation to visit the writer in Indianapolis with offer of a pass on the Bellefontaine Line.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1856 Aug. 18; Farnham, M. (Box 4)
    Letter enclosing pension voucher for Sept. 4 and advising there is little hope for Parker's petition to have his pension increased.
  - ALS to George W. Manypenny, 1856 Sept. 25; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Copy of a letter advising the Commissioner that the Tonawandas are about to send a delegation to Washington to protest the appointment of another agent to disburse the Ogden improvement money.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1856 Sept. 29; Manypenny, George W. (Box 4)
    An acknowledgment of Ely's letter of Sept. 25 stating that he sees no necessity for sending a delegation to Washington, as the Office of Indian Affairs does not contemplate appointing an agent to pay the improvement fund.
  - Letters of Marcus H. Johnson, Frederick Follett, N.E. Paine, and I.A. Verplank, to Franklin Pierce, William L. Marcy and R. McClelland., 1856 Oct. 8-13 (Box 4)
    Copies of letters protesting the appointment of an agent to disburse the Ogden improvement fund.
  - ADfS to Franklin Pierce, 1856 Oct. 17; Parker, Ely S. and Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Draft of a petition to the President summarizing the Ogden Co.'s efforts to appraise improvements at Tonawanda and the Indians' refusal to accept any part of the Company's "award" for same.
  - Memorandum, 1856 Oct. 21; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Memorandum concerning the Tonawanda delegation's conference with the President, F. Pierce, to present the Indians' protest against the appointment of a new agent to pay the Ogden Co.'s improvement fund.
  - Membership certificate in Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1856 Dec. 22; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Signed by Horatio Gates Jones, Secretary.
  - Abstract of Fellows v. Blacksmith and Parker, 1856 Dec.; United States. Supreme Court (Box 4)
    Printed abstract of case of Joseph Fellows, plaintiff, vs. Blacksmith and Parker, defendants. Joshua L. Brown, counsel for plaintiff.
  - Tonawanda Band, 1856 ? (Box 4)
    List of "Goods for 1856" consisting of blankets, calico, etc., valued at $611.49.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1857 Jan. 5; Cooper Hewitt and Co. (Box 4)
    A letter, addressed to Ely as Superintendent of the U.S. Marine Hospital, Galena, Ill., concerning the Company's willingness to adjust their error in weighing girders.
  - ALS to I. Newton Parker, 1857 Jan. 8; M. Stagers and Co. (Box 4)
    The Company wants to know if Newton and his troupe can be depended on to join their show next summer.
  - ALS to Wann and Gray, 1857 Jan. 17; McCarty, Michael (Box 4)
    Copy in E.S. Parker's hand of an amendment to a proposal to sell to the U.S. a site for the new Marine Hospital, Galena. The amendment concerns the location of the section to be retained for McCarty's own use.
  - Memorandum, 1857 Jan. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Memorandum of the points made by R.H. Gillett in the Argument before the U.S. Supreme Court in the Tonawanda case.